<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on CRC - Run OpenShift 4 on your laptop</title><link>https://crc.dev/blog/posts/</link><description>CRC - Run OpenShift 4 on your laptop (Posts)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 16:08:10 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://crc.dev/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Running crc on M1 machines</title><link>https://crc.dev/blog/posts/2022-04-04-vfkit/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 16:08:10 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://crc.dev/blog/posts/2022-04-04-vfkit/</guid><description>&lt;p>CRC can be used on a MacBook to run an OpenShift cluster or podman containers. However this support was limited to x86_64 CPUs until recently.
With Apple&amp;rsquo;s ongoing switch to aarch64 M1 CPUs, we&amp;rsquo;ve been asked numerous times when CRC would get M1 support.
This has changed with the recently released &lt;a href="https://github.com/code-ready/crc/releases/tag/v2.4.1">crc 2.4.1&lt;/a>.
This blog post will describe the challenges we had to overcome when we decided to add that support.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="background" >Background
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#background">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>CRC runs its OpenShift cluster/podman runtime by starting a virtual machine (VM) using a disk image built in advance and packaged in what we call a &lt;em>bundle&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On macOS, we use &lt;a href="https://github.com/moby/hyperkit">hyperkit&lt;/a> as our
hypervisor. It has served us well over the years, but lately it hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen a
lot of maintainance, and we&amp;rsquo;ve been hitting a few annoying bugs in its &lt;a href="https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-qcow">ocaml
qcow2 implementation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, the main problem with hyperkit is that it&amp;rsquo;s x86_64 only. It does not
provide any M1 support, so we had to look for alternatives if we want to run
CRC on a M1 mac.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="qemu-and-virtualizationframework" >QEMU and virtualization.framework
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#qemu-and-virtualizationframework">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>When looking for hypervisors we could use on macOS, we found two candidates:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.qemu.org/">QEMU&lt;/a> with its &lt;a href="https://wiki.qemu.org/Features/HVF">hvf acceleration&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apple&amp;rsquo;s own &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/virtualization">virtualization framework&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="qemu" >QEMU
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#qemu">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>QEMU is a widely used hypervisor on Linux systems, but it can also be used on
Windows and macOS. On macOS, it can use Apple&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/hypervisor">hypervisor
framework&lt;/a> to make use of
virtualization support in hardware.
It has a huge range of features. In particular it supports many virtio devices including &lt;a href="https://virtio-fs.gitlab.io/">virtiofs&lt;/a> for file sharing,
Its main drawback is that for supply chain trust reasons, we&amp;rsquo;d have to maintain
our own QEMU builds, which can be quite an endeavour given the size of QEMU&amp;rsquo;s
code base (2 million lines of C code).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="apples-virtualization-framework" >Apple&amp;rsquo;s virtualization framework
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#apples-virtualization-framework">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This is a &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/virtualization">high level Objective-C/swift framework&lt;/a> to start virtual machines on Apple hardware with a small set of virtio devices (disk, network, &amp;hellip;).
It was introduced in macOS &amp;lsquo;Big Sur&amp;rsquo; 11.0, and only supports macOS and Linux virtual machines. Luckily, our bundle is a Linux image, so it&amp;rsquo;s good enough for us!
It obviously supports both x86_64 and M1 CPUs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Its main advantage and drawback is that it&amp;rsquo;s a high-level framework maintained by Apple. This means very little code is needed to create a virtual machine with it, and Apple maintains and updates all the low-level virtualization code for us.
This is also a drawback, as this framework is closed source. This means we fully depend on Apple for fixing any bugs that we might find. And unfortunately, we&amp;rsquo;ve already hit such bugs in Apple&amp;rsquo;s implementation of virtiofs, a &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/bug-reporting/">bug has been filed&lt;/a>, but we have no control over when it will get fixed, if ever.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="introducing-vfkit" >Introducing vfkit
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#introducing-vfkit">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Apple&amp;rsquo;s virtualization framework looks promising, but it&amp;rsquo;s just a framework. A framework is similar to a shared library on Linux, your code can link to it to use what it offers, but you can&amp;rsquo;t directly use it as a commandline or GUI tool.
One particular caveat with the virtualization framework is that any virtual machines you start with it will only stay alive as long as the process which started it is alive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We could not find any pre-existing FOSS commandline tool to manage virtual machines with Apple&amp;rsquo;s virtualization framework, but luckily for us, there are &lt;a href="https://github.com/Code-Hex/vz">go bindings for it&lt;/a>.
This allowed us to write a small commandline wrapper using these bindings which we called &lt;a href="https://github.com/code-ready/vfkit">&lt;code>vfkit&lt;/code>&lt;/a>
It does not cover all features exposed by &lt;code>Code-Hex/vz&lt;/code> and the virtualization framework, but we can expand this over time. At the moment, its commandline is enough for CRC&amp;rsquo;s needs, including support for both system and usermode networking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="where-were-at" >Where we&amp;rsquo;re at
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#where-were-at">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>With &lt;code>vfkit&lt;/code>, we have a way of starting virtual machines on M1 hardware. The second thing that we need is a bundle with the appropriate disk images. The two main changes we had to do were:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>move from qcow2 to raw disk images as this is the only format Apple&amp;rsquo;s virtualization framework supports. This meant modifying CRC to make use of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sparse_file">sparse files&lt;/a> as much as possible to minimize disk usage. The &lt;a href="https://www.manpagez.com/man/2/clonefile/">&lt;code>clonefile&lt;/code>&lt;/a> system call was also very handy to limit the amount of disk space that we use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the &lt;a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/arm64/booting.txt">aarch64 kernel &lt;strong>must&lt;/strong> be uncompressed&lt;/a>, otherwise the virtual machine won&amp;rsquo;t start. This is fairly tedious to figure out as you don&amp;rsquo;t get any output from the virtual machine to let you know what went wrong.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After these changes, we were able to generate a podman bundle to use natively on a M1 machine. As its x86_64 counterpart, this bundle is built on top of Fedora CoreOS.
Running OpenShift on a M1 CPU won&amp;rsquo;t be possible soon, as it&amp;rsquo;s currently based on Red Hat CoreOS 8, and &lt;a href="https://access.redhat.com/solutions/6545411">its kernel is incompatible with M1 CPUs&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>vfkit&lt;/code> support for x86_64 hardware landed in crc 2.3.0 release, and so far did not have many issues reported.
We merged M1 vfkit support in crc 2.4.1, but had last minute issues related to signing, so it&amp;rsquo;s only available as an &lt;a href="https://github.com/code-ready/crc/releases/download/v2.4.1/crc-macos-unsigned-arm64.pkg">unsigned installer&lt;/a> for this release. Hopefully this will be solved in time for crc 2.5.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As usual, we&amp;rsquo;d like to get as much &lt;a href="https://github.com/code-ready/crc/issues/new/choose">feedback&lt;/a> as possible on all this work!&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>